Guide to the Bill Dixon Papers MSS.481
Fales Library and Special Collections
Bill Dixon Papers
1936-2012
1960-2010
Fales Library and Special Collections
Dixon, Bill, 1925-2010
Vogel, Sharon
MSS.481
182.45 Linear Feet in 33 record cartons, 47 flat boxes, 18 tall LP boxes, 94 manuscript boxes, 14 CD Boxes, 7 oversize flat boxes, 1 rolled storage box, and 2 flat-file folders
482.725 Gigabytes in 3,533 digital files.
227 VHS
1851 audiocassettes
627 sound tape reels
24 Sound_Disc--Vinyl
33 Half_Inch_Video_Reel
33 Betacam
50 U-matic
29 1_Inch_Video_Reel
1 2_Inch_Videoreel
32 film reels
Bill Dixon (1925-2010) was an educator, artist, composer, writer, and jazz musician who played the trumpet, flugelhorn, and piano. In 1968, he became a professor at Bennington College and established the Black Music Division in the 1970s. During his time at Bennington, he taught classes and was the conductor for the Black Music Ensemble. Dixon worked for fifty years as a recording artist, composer, and performer within the avant-garde jazz scene. The Bill Dixon Papers contain material from all facets of Dixon's personal and professional career in music, education, and visual arts. Dixon's music career is represented in the collection through analog and digital recordings of albums, sessions, and performances as well as paper and electronic work files, performance ephemera, and music manuscripts. Dixon's career at Bennington College is reflected in audiovisual recordings and paper files related to Division meetings, class lectures, rehearsals, and musical events. Materials on Dixon's activities outside Bennington College include audiovisual recordings and files related to lectures, appearances, Judson Arts Workshops, the University of the Streets, and his visiting professorship at the University of Wisconsin, Madison. His work as both a visual artist and writer is represented in this collection through artworks, reproductions, exhibition files, publications, and work files for projects including his book L'Opera: A Collection of Letters, Writings, Musical Scores, Drawings, and Photographs (1967-1986). His personal files include photographs, press clippings, interviews, correspondence, and resumes.
Conditions Governing Access
Restricted materials in Series II.A, II.C, and III are notated as such in the record's title. Please contact NYU Special Collections with specific questions regarding access to such records.
Donor permission is required for access to films 481_1034 and 481_1035. Please contact NYU Special Collections, special.collections@nyu.edu, 212-998-2596.
All other materials are open without restrictions.
Immediate Source of Acquisition
Donated by Sharon Vogel in March, 2017; the accession number associated with this gift is 2017.022.
Appraisal
Materials containing private student information, including Bennington College mid-term and final student evaluations, class lists, and correspondence discussing student performance, were deaccessioned along with audio recordings of Trustee Meetings and 24 blank compact discs. 103 commercial audiovisual recordings that did not feature Bill Dixon's work were separated from the collection.
In June 2023, 7 videotapes were deaccessioned after they were found to be blank tapes or commercial recordings of television programs.
In September 2024, 2 videotapes were deaccessioned after they were found to be blank tapes or duplicative content.
In September 2025, 6 blank films and 1 commercially available film were deaccessioned.
Arrangement
This collection is organized into five series. The first two series are arranged into three subseries.
Series I. Music
Subseries I.A. Commercial and Studio Recordings
Subseries I.B. Performance Recordings
Subseries I.C. Sheet Music, Work Files, and Performance Ephemera
Series II. Bennington College
Subseries II.A. Class and Lecture Recordings
Subseries II.B. Performance and Event Recordings
Subseries II.C. Teaching and Administrative Files
Series III. Educational Programs and Appearances
Series IV. Visual and Written Artwork
Series V. Personal Files
Files made up of multiple types of records (audio, video, paper, electronic, etc) have a child element for each type of record present.
Biographical Note
Jazz musician, composer, artist, and educator William (Bill) Robert Dixon was born in Nantucket, Massachusetts in 1925. Around the age of seven, he and his family moved to Harlem, New York. Dixon studied painting at Boston University, the WPA Arts School, and the Art Students League, working in a variety of mediums. Dixon served in the Army during World War II in Germany from 1944-1946, and later studied music at the Hartnett Conservatory of Music from 1946-1951 where he played trumpet, flugelhorn, and piano.
While living in New York in the 1950s, Dixon worked as an international civil servant at the United Nations and helped found the UN Jazz Society. Dixon also worked clubs as a performing musician in Greenwich Village during this time. In 1964, Dixon organized and produced a four-day festival of underexposed talent, the October Revolution in Jazz, including music and discussions, which led to him founding the short-lived cooperative organization of creative improvising New York musicians known as the Jazz Composers Guild.
In 1966, he began a collaborative partnership with dancer and choreographer Judith Dunn, which eventually led to him joining the faculty at Bennington College as a professor. Dixon founded the Black Music Division in the 1970s at Bennington. He assembled and led the Division's faculty and wrote the curriculum until his retirement from Bennington in 1995. While at Bennington, he taught classes in a variety of related subjects including improvisation, composition, and performance. He was director of the Black Music Ensemble. From 1971-1972, Dixon was a visiting professor of Music at the University of Wisconsin, Madison. He retired from Bennington College in 1996.
In addition to his work as an educator, Dixon continued to record music and perform among other improvisational jazz musicians. He played alongside Archie Shepp, Cecil Taylor, William Parker and other musicians of the avant-garde jazz scene. He worked for fifty years as a recording artist, crafting solo music for trumpet, ensemble, dance collaborations, and orchestras. He recorded with record labels RCA, Cadence Jazz Records, and Soul Note, and founded his own publishing company, Metamorphosis Music. In 1967, he composed and conducted a score for the United States Information Agency film The Wealth of a Nation, produced and directed by William Greaves. In 1980, Dixon completed his first tour in Italy, where he would return to record the albums In Italy, Vol I and II, and Considerations, Vol I and II. In 2007, Dixon recorded 17 Musicians in Search of a Sound: Darfur at the New York City Vision Festival to bring attention to the genocide of Sudan's South Darfur region.
Dixon was also an artist working in various mediums including painting, printmaking, drawing, and collage. He often used his visual art on album covers. As an author, he published the book L'Opera: A Collection of Letters, Writings, Musical Scores, Drawings, and Photographs in 1986. He also wrote reviews and articles, and contributed to other books about jazz.
Bill Dixon passed away in 2010.
Born-Digital Access Policies and Procedures
Advance notice is required for the use of computer records. Original physical digital media is restricted.
An access terminal for born-digital materials in the collection is available by appointment for reading room viewing and listening only. Researchers may view an item's original container and/or carrier, but the physical carriers themselves are not available for use because of preservation concerns.
Audiovisual Access Policies and Procedures
Access to some audiovisual materials in this collection is available through digitized access copies. Researchers may view an item's original container, but the media themselves are not available for playback because of preservation concerns. Materials that have already been digitized are noted in the collection's finding aid and can be requested in our reading room. To request an access copy, or if you are unsure if an item has been digitized, please contact special.collections@nyu.edu with the collection name, collection number, and a description of the item(s) requested. A staff member will respond to you with further information.
Some audiovisual materials have not been preserved and may not be available to researchers. Materials not yet digitized will need to have access copies made before they can be used. To request an access copy, or if you are unsure if an item has been digitized, please contact Fales Library and Special Collections (special.collections@nyu.edu, 212-998-2596) with the collection name, collection number, and a description of the item(s) requested. A staff member will respond to you with further information.
Scope and Contents
The Bill Dixon Papers (1936-2012) contains audiovisual, paper, and digital materials documenting Dixon's life and work as a jazz musician, composer, educator, visual artist, and writer.
This collection contains material created during his lifetime career as a jazz musician and composer, particularly the free jazz, experimental music, and avant-garde jazz scenes, dating from the 1960s through 2010. Dixon's large collection of analog and digital audiovisual recordings include performances, rehearsals, radio broadcasts, film soundtracks, and album recording sessions. Paper files support these recordings with handwritten sheet music, correspondence, work files, performance ephemera, and still images of practices, recordings, and performances.
Class curricula, lecture notes, and administrative files document Dixon's tenure as a professor at Bennington College from 1968 to his retirement in 1995. Correspondence, notes, and reports document Dixon's role founding the Black Music Division and his involvement with the Black Music Ensemble. Images portray students, faculty, rehearsals and classes. Audiovisual recordings include Dixon's class lectures (1970s-1990s), music lessons and workshops, student and faculty performances, rehearsals, Black Music Division events, and Division meetings.
This collection also documents Dixon's educational appearances and activities outside of Bennington College. Audiovisual recordings, photographs, and paper files document Dixon's lecture series, panels, and workshops. Notable programs include the Judson Arts Workshops, the University of the Streets, and his visiting professorship at the University of Wisconsin, Madison (Fall 1971 to Spring 1972).
Dixon's work as a visual artist is represented in both original artworks and reproductions of his work, which include photography, collage, printworking, painting, and ink and pencil drawings. The collection also contains tools used in art creation such as printing blocks, an etching plate, and linoleum block sheets. Work files contain correspondence, notes, and images of the creation process and finished works.
As a writer, Dixon produced articles, reviews, book contributions, liner notes for fellow musicians' albums, dating from the 1950s to the 2000s. Many of his writings pertain to his experiences as a jazz musician, compositions, and relationships with other musicians. This collection contains original publications and work files on many of his writings. Work files for his book L'Opera: A Collection of Letters, Writings, Musical Scores, Drawings, and Photographs (1967-1986) contain notes, drafts, mock-ups, correspondence, and the book itself. Also of note are his writings concerning his partnership with the choreographer Judith Dunn, with whom he collaborated in the 1960s and 1970s.
Audiovisual recordings, photographs, correspondence, datebooks, press clippings, resumes, and scholarly works and interviews provide a profile of his life and work.
Related Materials
For more information about the Black Music Division at Bennington College, see Bennington College History: Black Music LibGuide: https://libraryguides.bennington.edu/blackmusic
Jazz musicians -- United States; African American jazz musicians; Free jazz.; Jazz musicians -- New York (State) -- New York -- Interviews.; Jazz -- History; Ensembles (musical groups); Clippings (information artifacts); Correspondence.; Musical performance.; Sheet music.; Black-and-white photographs.; Color photographs.; Personal correspondence.; Art, American -- 21st century; Art, American -- 20th century; linoleum blocks; printing blocks (printing surfaces); Sound recordings; Vogel, Sharon; Judson Memorial Church (New York, N.Y.); Shepp, Archie; WKCR (Radio station: New York, N.Y.); Cook, Laurence; Pavone, Mario; Qamar, Nadi; Taylor, Cecil, 1929-2018; Oxley, Tony; Horenstein, Stephen; Dunn, Judith; Brooks, Arthur; Bennington College
- Series I. Music, 1936, 1941, 1959-2012; 125.72 Linear Feet in 30 record cartons, 39 flat boxes, 17 tall LP boxes, 24 manuscript boxes, 5 oversize flat boxes, 1 rolled storage box, and 2 flat-file folders.; 402.54 Gigabytes in 1,214 digital files.
  Scope and Contents
  This series contains analog and digital audiovisual recordings spanning Dixon's musical career, including published albums, features on albums by other artists, film soundtracks, radio broadcasts, recording sessions, solo and ensemble performances, orchestral performances, music festivals, and choreographed collaborations with Judith Dunn. It also contains paper and digital documentation of his work as a musician, including album related work files, music manuscripts, performance ephemera, and annotated reference books.
  - Subseries I.A: Commercial and Studio Recordings, 1960-2012; 45 Linear Feet in 23 flat boxes, 16 record cartons, 3 LP boxes, 1 manuscript box, and 1 cassette box
    Arrangement
    This subseries is arranged chronologically. Undated items are arranged alphabetically at the end of the subseries. Wherever possible, record titles were transcribed directly from audiovisual labels and edited minimally to provide context.
    This subseries includes recordings from Dixon's published albums spanning his career from the 1960s to 2009; features on albums by other artists, such as Cecil Taylor, Tony Oxley, and Arthur Brooks; music written for films, including Wealth of a Nation (1966); radio broadcasts, including several programs on Columbia University's WKCR that showcased different eras of Dixon's career and celebrated his birthdays; recording sessions for record labels such as RCA, Soulnote, and Cadence Jazz, as well as unissued private recordings; and compilation and demo tapes handmade by Bill Dixon and distributed via Metamorphosis Music.
    - Compilation Tape, circa 1960s; cuid8713 (Box 58, Quarter inch audio reel 481_1459)
    - A Compilation Through 1976: "Places and Things", "Letter", circa 1960s-1976; cuid36465 (Box 43, Audiocassette 481_2491)
    - Compilation Tape -- "Metamorphosis," "Voices," "Orchestra Piece," "Sequences", 1962-1972; cuid36480 (Box 41, Audiocassette 481_1962)
    - Compilation Tape -- Ayler / Taylor WBAI Demo, Bill Dixon Orchestra Session, 1962-1979; cuid36481 (Box 41, Audiocassette 481_1963)
    - Compilation Tape -- Intents and Purposes, Considerations 1, Considerations 2, circa 1962-1979; cuid36466 (Box 34, Audiocassette 481_1536)
    - Compilation Tape -- Music Excerpts, 1962-1986; cuid36473 (Box 42, Audiocassette 481_2040)
    - Scandinavian Sketches, WBAI, February 21, 1963; cuid36484 (Box 18, Quarter inch audio reel 481_1321)
      Physical Characteristics and Technical Requirements
      Duration: 30 minutes
    - Dixon Demo Tape -- Unissued Only, 1963-1964; cuid36482 (Box 41, Audiocassette 481_1995)
    - Compilation Tape -- "Miscellaneous Music", circa 1963-2000; cuid36483 (Box 35, Audiocassette 481_1577)
    - Bill Dixon 7-Tette / Archie Shepp and the New York Contemporary 5, March 5, 1964; cuid36486 (Box 82, Cd 481_1927)
      Published by Atlantic Recording Corporation
    - Compilation Tape -- "Miscellaneous Music", 1964-2000; cuid36485 (Box 36, Audiocassette 481_1632)
    - The Bill Dixon -- Archie Shepp Quartet, circa 1966; cuid36471 (Box 18, Sound disc--vinyl 481_1013)
    - "Dew Horse II," Judson Memorial Church, July 11, 1966; cuid36495 (Box 18, Sound disc--lacquer 481_1011)
      Duration: 19 minutes; Preservation note: Surface damage some skipping
    - "I Remember", 1966; cuid36488 (Box 18, Sound disc--lacquer 481_1019)
    - "Large Orchestra Piece" (Version I), circa 1966; cuid36472 (Box 18, Sound disc--lacquer 481_1015, 481_1018)
    - "Large Orchestra Piece" (Version II), circa 1966; cuid36468 (Box 18, Sound disc--lacquer 481_1009)
    - "Metamorphosis I", circa 1966; cuid36469 (Box 18, Sound disc--lacquer 481_1010)
    - "Metamorphosis / Groundspeed", July, 1966; cuid36494 (Box 18, Sound disc--lacquer 481_1016)
    - "Metamorphosis" Recording Session, RCA Victor, October 10, 1966; cuid36497 (Box 16, Quarter inch audio reel 481_1393)
      This tape was rehoused; the original housing with annotations was kept and labeled with same identifier
    - "Motorcycle", circa 1966; cuid36470 (Box 18, Sound disc--lacquer 481_1012)
      Duration: 35 minutes; Preservation note: Surface damage some skipping
    - "Nouveau Ne / Motorcycle", 1966; cuid36487 (Box 18, Sound disc--lacquer 481_1014)
    - "Pomegranate", July 11, 1966; cuid36496 (Box 18, Sound disc--lacquer 481_1017)
    - Wealth of a Nation, circa 1966; cuid36467 (Box 69, Vhs 481_1060)
      Duration: 22 minutes
    - WKCR Broadcast -- "Pomegranate," "Dew Horse I," "Dew Horse II," "Solo," "Untitled Ensemble Piece with Voices", 1966; cuid36489 (Box 35, Audiocassette 481_1591)
    - Intents and Purposes by the Bill Dixon Orchestra, RCA Victor, New York City, 1966-1967; cuid36474
    - WKCR Compilation Tape -- Judson Memorial Performances, Large Orchestra Piece, 1966-1968; cuid36490 (Box 41, Audiocassette 481_1964)
    - WKCR Broadcast -- "Octobersong / Conversation Winter Tales," "Nouveau Ne," "Three Short Pieces," "Motorcycle" at Judson Memorial Church, 1966-1970; cuid36491 (Box 35, Audiocassette 481_1579)
    - Compilation Tape -- Works from 1966-1985, cuid36492 (Box 37, Audiocassette 481_1673)
    - Original Musical Compositions Performed in Concert and on Recording, 1966-1990; cuid36493 (Box 42, Audiocassette 481_2052)
      Handmade cassette published by Bill Dixon, Inc. and Metamorphosis Music, BMI
    - Compilation Disc, 1966-1993; cuid36475
    - Compilation Tape -- Trumpet and Saxophone, circa 1967; cuid36478 (Box 54, Quarter inch audio reel 481_1338)
    - Intents and Purposes, circa 1967; cuid36477
    - Intents and Purposes, Danspace QT, circa 1967; cuid36476
    - Trumpet Overdubbings by Bill Dixon, recorded at George Washington University and published by Metamorphosis Music, BMI, NYC, 1967; cuid36498 (Box 54, Quarter inch audio reel 481_1327)
    - "Voices" RCA Victor Rehearsal, circa 1967
      Featuring Byard Lancaster (Bass Clarinet), Kathi Norris (Cello), Bob Pozar (Drums), Jimmie Garrison (Bass), Bill Dixon (Trumpet, flugelhorn, composer)
      - Audio, cuid36479 (Box 64, Quarter inch audio reel 481_1094)
      - Papers (Box 213, Folder 10)
    - UPAI and "Voices" Recording Sessions, RCA Victor, January 17, 1967; cuid36499 (Box 64, Quarter inch audio reel 481_1092)
      Featuring Byard Lancaster (Bass Clarinet), Kathi Norris (Cello), Bob Pozar (Drums), Jimmie Garrison (Bass), Bill Dixon (Trumpet, Flugelhorn, Composer)
    - "Nightfall Pieces" No. I and No. II, RCA Victor, February 21, 1967; cuid36500 (Box 64, Quarter inch audio reel 481_1093)
      Featuring Bill Dixon and George Marge
    - "Mosaic", 1969-1970; cuid36501
    - 1982, 1970; cuid36502 (Box 18, Sound disc--vinyl 481_1008)
      Some signed artwork and an exhibition booklet were originally stored with this record; they removed and foldered separately.
    - WKCR Broadcast: "Untitled," "Untitled," "Piece for Karen Lierly", 1970-1971; cuid36504 (Box 35, Audiocassette 481_1592)
    - Compilation Disc, circa 1970s; cuid36503
      This disc includes "For Franz," Bill Dixon and Cecil Taylor, "Index," "Voices"
    - Dixon Trumpet Solos -- Some Used on Odyssey, circa 1970s; cuid36505 (Box 52, Quarter inch audio reel 481_442)
    - Bill Dixon on WMFM Radio, November 22, 1971; cuid36513 (Box 64, Quarter inch audio reel 481_1025, Box 57, Quarter inch audio reel 481_1448)
    - Compilation Disc, 1971-1974; cuid36506
      This disc includes Orchestra Pieces, Bennington College Performances, and Madison, Wisconsin Orchestras
    - In the Sign of the Labyrinth: "Summerdance," "Bennet," "Mirrors," "Sotto Voce", 1971-1975; cuid36510 (Box 18, Sound disc--vinyl 481_1505)
      Published by FORE
    - Compilation Tape -- "Summerdance," "Mirrors," "Sotto Voce", 1971-1976; cuid36508 (Box 34, Audiocassette 481_1529)
    - Compilation Tape -- Works from 1971-1976, cuid36507 (Box 36, Audiocassette 481_1640)
    - FORE Record (Live Overdub), circa 1971-1976; cuid36796 (Box 44, Audiocassette 481_2513)
    - FORE Recording, circa 1971-1976; cuid36774 (Box 34, Audiocassette 481_1520)
    - In the Sign of the Labyrinth: "This is Our Strategy," "Letters to Myself", 1971-1976; cuid36509 (Box 18, Sound disc--vinyl 481_1504)
    - Madison Black Music Ensemble Rehearsal for WHA TV 21, 1972; cuid36514 (Box 69, Vhs 481_1070)
      Transferred from 2" video
      Duration: 63 minutes
    - In the Sign of the Labyrinth: "Trident," "Triumvirate," "Trilogy," "Trident II," "Trident III," "Letters to Myself", 1972-1974; cuid36515 (Box 18, Sound disc--vinyl 481_1507)
    - Compilation Disc, 1972-1976; cuid36516
      This disc includes "This Is Our Strategy," Ensemble Performance, Autumn Festival, Solos
    - Compilation Tape -- "Summerdance," "Piece for Pat Lagg," "Trumpet and Child's Voice," "This is Our Strategy," "Trumpet and Piano I," "Trumpet and Piano II", 1972-1976; cuid36517 (Box 34, Audiocassette 481_1533)
    - "Letters" Version B, Orchestra Piece Related to "Letters", 1973-1974; cuid36519 (Box 26, Audiocassette 481_628)
    - "Webern Work Study", circa 1973-1974; cuid36518
    - Compilation Tape -- Solo Trumpet, Solo Piano, "This Is Our Strategy", 1973-1976; cuid36520 (Box 35, Audiocassette 481_1590)
    - Compilation Tape --"Shrike," "Webern," "Another Quiet Feeling," "Nobody Knows My Name", 1973-1985; cuid36521 (Box 34, Audiocassette 481_1519)
    - Guggenheim Tape, 1974; cuid36522 (Box 61, Quarter inch audio reel 481_2296)
    - Ensemble Muntu Featuring Mark Hannen, Jemeel Moondoc, May 20, 1974; cuid36528 (Box 59, Quarter inch audio reel 481_2075)
    - Brass Duos -- Issued and Unissued, May 30, 1974; cuid8723 (Box 60, Quarter inch audio reel 481_2143)
      Housing annotations: "As issued on Force Five (Duo #1); unissued (Duo #2)"
    - Compilation Disc, 1974-1975; cuid36523
      This disc includes WKCR Broadcast 73rd Birthday, Oxley-Dixon-Guy in Nickelsdorf, BY, "Papyrus," "This Is Our Strategy," Orchestra Piece, Bird's Word
    - Compilation of Orchestra Works, 1974-1975; cuid36524
    - In the Sign of the Labyrinth: "Line," "Chiaroscuro," "Aquerelle," "Imprimatura," "Movementum," "Piece for Pat Lagg," "Triplex", 1974-1976; cuid36525 (Box 18, Sound disc--vinyl 481_1506)
    - Compilation Tape -- Music Excerpts, Including Orchestra Works and Quartets, 1974-1988; cuid36526 (Box 42, Audiocassette 481_2050)
    - Compilation Disc, circa 1974-2007; cuid36527
      This disc includes "Shrike," "Papyrus," Henry Grimes and Bill Dixon, and United States Artists Music Submission
    - Compilation Disc, circa 1975; cuid36529
    - Guggenheim Grant Original Compositions, Fall, 1975; cuid36530 (Box 41, Audiocassette 481_1984)
    - Film Music for Chester Higgins, 1975-1976; cuid36531 (Box 24, Audiocassette 481_585)
    - Considerations 1, FORE 4, circa 1976; cuid36511 (Box 34, Audiocassette 481_1527)